Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and we've got a
very sad dialogue today actually Marco.
That's right today we have a very sad
but interesting dialogue of something that
happens all the time.
Maybe you have a
girlfriend, maybe you had a
boyfriend and you break up.
That means you are no longer
a boyfriend and girlfriend.
Let's take a listen to
today's dialogue and we'll
be back in a moment to
talk about what's going on.
Hey, do you want to go out tonight? No,
I think I'll pass. Mark broke up with me.
I feel awful. What? What
happened? Just last week
you were talking about
going on vacation together.
I don't know what I did wrong. He said
he needed some space to figure things out.
He said I didn't do anything wrong but I'm
a great person. Just not the one for him.
That's so cliche. Mark's not worth your
time Lydia. You deserve so much better.
I know we had hit a
rough patch but I had
hoped we could work it
out next weekend when
we both had some time off. I
think he found someone else.
I had been getting
suspicious because
he had been spending a
lot of time with a coworker.
Whatever. He's a
jerk. Forget about him.
There are many more fish in the sea. Talk
about being cliche Maggie but you're right.
There's no use for me to soak around.
Let's go out tonight.
All right. We're back
so obviously this girl
Lydia is very torn. She's
very sad because her
boyfriend broke up
with her. That's right.
She's crying the whole
time that's what's going on.
That's right. But she
did mention her and her
friend mentioned
some interesting things.
Why don't we take a look
at some of the words they
used on language
takeaway. Language takeaway.
So first of all her
friend says hey do you
want to go out tonight
and what does Lydia say?
She says no. I think
I'll pass. All right.
I think I'll pass. I will pass. So
what does this verb mean to pass?
So that means she is politely rejecting
the offer or the invitation. So no thanks.
No thanks. That's
basically what it means.
I won't go. So hey Marco
you want to go see a movie
in a couple hours?
No. I think I'll pass.
I got homework to do. All
right. So Marco will not come.
That means to decline
an invitation. That's right.
So that's what it means to pass.
Now as they continue to talk
they mentioned some of the
problems with their boyfriend
but Maggie said that's so cliche.
So the boyfriend said
something and Maggie
thinks that what he
said was very, very cliche.
So what is something
that is cliche?
Cliche means something
that is said or done very often.
It's almost like
we would expect it.
So like for example what's a
cliche phrase or a cliche action?
Well in the dialogue
they were talking about
ways of breaking up with
people. So for example it's not you.
It's me. Let's break up.
So that's a cliche because
it's a sentence. It's a phrase
everyone always says. It's not
very, maybe not very honest.
Or like a movie cliche would be
a couple. They're
getting married but their
parents, the parents of
the bride, they're divorced,
they hate each other. But
then at the wedding they
get back together. They're
going to get married again.
That's a cliche
story. That's right.
Because you've heard it
before. Right. All the time.
It's very common. So
something's very common.
Something that you would
expect to that's almost
that's a cliche. And a
cliche calling something
a cliche is not a good
thing. It's usually a bad thing.
That's right. Okay. So Maggie goes on to
say that this guy, Mark, her ex-boyfriend,
he's not really worth it. She
says you deserve so much better.
Okay. So to deserve is a verb and it
means that you should receive something or
you should expect
something. So almost like you
know in this case
you deserve better.
You have earned something
better. You're a good person.
You should receive a, you know,
you should have a good boyfriend.
That's right. So when
she says you deserve
so much better, she's
talking about deserving
a better guy, a better man. Or for example,
so Marco, you work so hard at school.
You're always doing your homework.
You really deserve good grades.
Okay. And you should
receive good grades.
Very good. Now when Lydia
said, yeah, you know what?
I just thought we were having some
problems and we had hit a rough patch.
So she's talking
about a rough patch.
What is that? A rough patch
is actually something we talk
about a lot in spoken
English. It's a way to describe
a period of time, so
maybe a week or a month,
when things are difficult,
you know, when maybe
you argue with your
boyfriend or girlfriend or
when you're sad a lot
or when you're confused.
And so a period of time
when you're angry or sad
with your boyfriend or
girlfriend, that's a rough patch.
So maybe we can apply a
rough patch to another situation.
Like at work, maybe
you're going through
a rough patch at work.
That means I'm always busy.
I'm always tired. I don't
feel happy with my job.
I'm going through a rough patch.
So it's usually a temporary period
of time where things are going bad.
It could be a week,
it could be a month,
it could be a year, but
it's a fixed amount of time.
It's not forever.
It's just a period.
Okay, very good. And Lydia
went on to say that, you
know, she thought that maybe he
was going out with someone else.
And she was suspicious because he was
spending a lot of time with some other girl.
Okay, so to be
suspicious is to think that
something is happening,
but you don't know.
So for example, Marco, I think
you've been taking the milk
from the kitchen. You
are always drinking coffee,
and you always take milk in your
coffee, and there's no more milk.
So I think it was you.
I'm being suspicious. I'm thinking
that maybe you did something
bad or wrong that I'm
guilty. So maybe you're
suspicious that someone
is stealing the milk or
maybe you suspect or
you're suspicious that your
next door neighbor is
maybe a car thief. Right.
So you're very suspicious.
That means you're always
thinking that this person or
someone else is doing something bad.
That's right. Okay.
So a lot of words they're talking
about relationships, talking about cliches.
Why don't we go
back, let's listen
to the dialogue again, and we'll
be back in a bit with fluency builder.
Hello. Hey, do you
want to go out tonight?
No, I think I'll pass.
Mark broke up with me.
I feel awful. What? What
happened? Just last week
you were talking about
going on vacation together?
I don't know what I did wrong.
He said he needed some space
to figure things out. He said,
I didn't do anything wrong, but I'm a
great person. Just not the one for him.
That's so cliche. Mark's not worth your
time, Lydia. You deserve so much better.
I know we had hit a rough
patch, but I had hoped
we could work it out next weekend
when we both had some time off.
I think he found someone else.
I had been getting suspicious
because he had been
spending a lot of time
with a coworker. Whatever.
He's a jerk. Forget about
him. There are many
more fish in the sea.
Talk about being cliche
Maggie, but you're right.
There's no use for me to
soak around. Let's go
out tonight. All right.
We're back. So now let's
take a look at some of
those phrases on Fluency
Builder. Fluency Builder.
All right. So Marco,
these are cliche phrases
that we hear in English
when people are breaking
up. Okay. So there's
some breaking up phrases,
but there's also phrases
that you might hear
from your friend after
you have a breakup. Okay.
The first phrase we're
going to look at, I
think, is to need space.
So he said he needed
some space. Right. And
that's a cliche phrase, as
we said, but it means that
maybe her ex-boyfriend
or Mark needs more space,
needs more time to be on
his own or needs more
time to do his own things.
That's right. So when
you're in a relationship,
you have a boyfriend or
girlfriend you're always together.
I need some space
means I want to be alone.
I don't want to be with
my boyfriend or girlfriend.
Sometimes this is
just a small period.
Sometimes it's forever.
It depends. That's right.
So when somebody says
that they need space, it
means they need a little
bit of more time to be
on their own or to
be alone, as you said.
And also he had also given
her another cliche phrase,
Mark said that she is not the one for him.
Okay. So the emphasis here is the one.
The one. She's not the
one for him. So in English,
we often talk about
the one. And this means
the person that you will
marry, the love of your
life, your your significant
other your other half.
That's right. And so you hope
that you will marry the one.
But her boyfriend realized he said,
"Listen, I like you, but you're not the one.
You're not the person
that I will marry." So
this is a phrase you
often hear and break up.
So if you're single, maybe
you don't have a boyfriend
or you're not married,
you might say that you
haven't found the one.
Or yeah, you have a lot of
different boyfriends, but
you still haven't found the one.
That means the
one you will marry.
That's right. Okay. Very
good. And now towards
the end of the dialogue, Maggie also gives
her some advice and said, "You know what?
Forget about him. There
are many more fish in the sea.
" Okay. So this is a
phrase that we often say
when we're trying to
make somebody feel better.
So the person is sad and
we want to make them happy.
And so there are many
more fish in the sea
means that there are
other men in the world.
Okay, you're sad. You
broke up. I understand,
but there are so many other men you could
date. So she's trying to say, "Hey, listen,
look at this world. There's
so many different options.
" That's right. So it's
the it's the similarity
of how in the sea you have
so many fish in the world.
You have so many men.
So don't worry about it.
And you can say this about
women too. So for example,
if I'm talking to my
male friend or my brother
and my brother just
broke up with his girlfriend,
I can say, "Hey, listen,
there are many more
fish in the sea. Many other
women." So don't worry about it.
Don't worry about
it. You'll be okay.
And Lydia says, "You know
what? I think you're right.
" And there's really no
use for me to soak around.
So what does she
mean to soak around?
To soak. Now this is something
that is very visual for me.
I see somebody
sulking their head is low.
They're sad. Someone who is sulking often
wears their sweatpants or their pajamas.
They don't they don't
make themselves look good.
To soak around means
to be in your house, to be
sad, to watch TV and eat
ice cream. So stop sulking.
Don't look sad. Be happy. So to soak is
to act sad and to, you know, be very down.
So it's kind of like you're very, it's
kind of a combination of being lazy but
and also sad at the same time
because something bad happened to you.
Exactly. And so we often say that in English
teenagers like to soak, you know, "Oh,
I'm so angry at my
parents." And your parents
will say, "Hey, stop sulking.
Go study." That's right.
Very good. Okay. So a lot of great
phrases here. I think we can go back.
Let's listen to this
dialogue one last time.
Hello? Hey, do you want to go out tonight?
No. I think I'll pass.
Mark broke up with me. I feel awful.
What? What happened?
Just last week you were
talking about going
on vacation together.
I don't know what I did wrong. He said
he needed some space to figure things out.
He said, "I didn't do anything
wrong but I'm a great person.
Just not the one for him."
That's so cliche. Mark's not worth your
time, Lydia. You deserve so much better.
I know we had hit a rough
patch but I had hoped
we could work it out next weekend
when we both had some time off.
I think he found someone else.
I had been getting suspicious
because he had been
spending a lot of time
with a coworker. Whatever.
He's a jerk. Forget about
him. There are many
more fish in the sea.
Talk about being cliche
Maggie but you're right.
There's no use for me to
soak around. Let's go
out tonight. All right.
So, talking about breakups, these cliche
lines and well Maggie's obviously upset.
What other cliche lines or breakup
phrases have you heard apart from?
It's not you. It's me.
You're just not the one. I need
some space. I hate some space.
I think of you more like
a friend because there's
a boyfriend or
girlfriend but then there's
a friend and so listen.
I like you but I think of
you more like a friend.
I think that's a typical
one especially if you're
asking someone out on a
date they might say that
you know oh I really like
you but I see you more as
a friend than anything else.
There's another one
that's very popular.
Sometimes you hear
people say I'm just not ready
for a relationship and
that's also a cliche line
or I'm not ready to
commit. I'm not ready to
commit yeah and it's
interesting because I think
breaking up is one of
the hardest things that
people can do and I think
maybe this is why you just
use one of these phrases
that are so popular in
common because I guess
it's kind of a good way
to explain in very soft
terms what you want to
say and to break up with
someone. That's right and
I think that sometimes
people are afraid to make
the other person sad and
so they say these things
that are very you know
general like it's not you it's me.
Right. But sometimes
this makes the other
person even more sad
because they don't understand
why that they're
breaking up so what about
breaking up over the telephone
or breaking up with a letter.
Oh generally at least in America we say
that breaking up over email or letter or
phone is not a good way to
end a relationship it's very cold.
It's very cold so the other person
would be very angry if that happened.
That's right you just want to
see the person and say listen
let's have a conversation let's
talk about this space to face.
Okay so this is actually very interesting
because as we say maybe in other countries
or in other cultures
is not really a negative
thing to break up over
the phone or maybe send
an email saying you know what
I don't want to see you anymore.
Right so I'd be
very curious to hear
about you guys and your
cultures and what happens
when people break
up where you live.
So let us know our website
is EnglishPod.com we hope to
see you there and of
course we hope that you
haven't had any very
bad big up experiences but
if you're comfortable
sharing we'd like to hear
about your culture and your background.
Alright so we'll see you guys there. Bye.